Finding aid to Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society, Smith College Chapter Records. CA.MS.00315
Smith College Archives
Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society, Smith College Chapter Records
1930-2007
Smith College Archives
Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. Smith College Chapter.
CA.MS.00315
3.771 linear feet (8 containers)
The Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society, Smith College Chapter records contain correspondence, minutes, programs, and committee records.
Biographical / Historical
The Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society, Smith College Chapter was granted its charter on December 28, 1934, the first charter ever granted to a women's institution. Throughout its history the chapter has undertaken many programs designed to encourage and support scientific research at Smith, both amongst its undergraduate students and its faculty. These programs include: a house academic competition, lecture series, participation in national meetings, and research and conference support. The chapter also nominates and elects new members each spring.
Scope and Contents
The Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society, Smith College Chapter records are very thorough, encompassing correspondence dating from 1931 to present, minutes and records from 1934 to present, membership lists from 1931 to present, and initiation programs from 1938 to present. The correspondence is mostly concerned with lectures, membership, and national Sigma Xi topics such as grant allocation.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society, Smith College Chapter records were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
- SERIES I. MINUTES AND OFFICIAL RECORDS
  - History of the Smith College Chapter, 1936 (Box 1122)
  - By-Laws of the Smith College Chapter, 1937-90 (Box 1122)
  - Petition for Charter - Faculty Publications, 1930-34 (Box 1122)
  - Petition for Establishment of Smith Chapter, 1931-35 (Box 1122)
  - Installation of the Chapter, 1935 (Box 1122)
  - Minutes and Records, 1934-53 (Box 1122)
  - Minutes and Records, 1953-85 (Box 1123)
  - Minutes and Records, 1985-ongoing (Box 1124)
  - Elected Officers, 1966-2006 (Box 1124)
  - President's Reports, 1935; 1940 (Box 1124)
  - Secretary's Notebooks and Reports, 1935-77 (Box 1124)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1953-84 (Box 1124)
  - Admissions Committee, 1938-60 (Box 1124)
  - Executive Committee, 1935-52 (Box 1124)
  - Membership Committee, 1940-62 (Box 1124)
  - Membership Committee: Certificates, 1953-82 (Box 1124)
  - Membership Committee: Membership Lists, 1931-ongoing (Box 1124)
  - Membership Committee: Roll of Members, 1935-80 (Box 1124)
  - Membership Certificate Order Forms, 1964-78 (Box 1124)
  - Membership Data Cards, 1935-68 (Box 1125)
  - Nominating Committee, 1936-84 (Box 1126)
  - Nominating Committee: Nomination Forms, 1970-71 (Box 1126)
  - Nominating Committee: Nomination Forms, 1972-91 (Box 1126)
  - Initiation Information, 1970; undated (Box 1126)
  - Initiation Ceremony, 1958-85 (Box 1126)
  - Initiation Correspondence, 1944-78 (Box 1126)
  - Initiation Procedures, 1945-63 (Box 1126)
  - Initiation Programs, 1938-92 (Box 1126)
  - Insignia, 1963 (Box 1126)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence, 1930-ongoing (Box 1127)
- SERIES III. ACTIVITIES
  - Anniversary (semi-centennial celebration), 1936 (Box 1128)
  - Annual Meeting (National) ( 3 folders), 1984-88 (Box 1128)
  - Awards - House Award Certificate, undated (Box 1128)
  - Awards - Special Research Awards, 1932-34 (Box 1128)
  - Awards - House Plaque, 1939-63 (Box 1128)
  - Caen University Letter of Appreciation for Gift, 1946 (Box 1128)
  - Certificates of Recognition from National Committee on Qualifications and Membership, 1997-2007 (Box 1128)
  - Committee on Long Range Planning National Committee Meeting at Smith College, 1985 (Box 1128)
  - Connecticut Valley Student Scientific Conference, 1953-56 (Box 1128)
  - Forum on Global Change and Our Common Future, 1989 (Box 1128)
  - Lectures (3 folders), 1935-96 (Box 1128)
  - Luncheon Lectures, 1940; 1977-85 (Box 1128)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1128)
  - National Lectures, 1986-90 (Box 1128)
  - National Sigma Xi Information, 1944; 1970 (Box 1128)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1935-95 (Box 1128)
  - Photographs, 1935-48 (Box 1128)
  - Princeton Study, 1948-49 (Box 1128)
  - Proposed Merger of Sigma Xi and RESA, 1949-53 (Box 1128)
  - Publications - General, 1936-95 (Box 1128)
  - Publications - Smith, 1937-49 (Box 1128)
  - Science Legislation, undated (Box 1128)
  - Student Subsidies for Conference Travel, 1989 (Box 1128)
- SERIES IV. ARTIFACTS
  - Robert's Rules of Order, revised, 1950 (Box 1129)
  - 2 die cut logos, 1959; undated (Box 1129)
  - Award plaque, oversized, undated (Box 1129)